# Patrick C. Wilkins

182 Golflinks Drive Ottawa, Ontario, K2J 5M T: 613-692-7701 pat.wilkins@gmail.com

#### **PROFILE**

Senior System Engineer / Architect with broad MIS experience in both technical and management capacities. Has demonstrated skills in architecting and building web based portals and applications for wire-line and wireless customers. Effective use of business process analysis, System Engineering and Project Management skills allow him to deliver business-to-business and business-to-consumer "e" services that permit a quick return on investment. Mr. Wilkins currently holds a Top Secret Clearance (PWGSC / DND).

#### **SKILLS INVENTORY:**

### **Programming Languages:**

HTML; CSS5; PHP; JavaScript; Jscript; ActionScript 3; Flash; Java, Visual Basic; Pascal; C; DCF; PL/1; Cobol.

### **Development Environments:**

WordPress; FLASH Professional; MS Visual Studio.NET, MS Visual Studio 6.0; MS Visual Source Safe, Rational Rose Modeler, Rational ClearQuest, Rational RequisitePro, Rational ClearCase, Rational SoDA, Rational Unified Process

### PC / MAC:

MS Office; MsProject; WAMP; Adobe Master Collection CS5, MS-Access; MS Groove; Oracle; Foxpro; Visio.

#### **Protocols**

HTML; WML; XML; cXML; TCP/IP; UDP/IP; Netbeui; NetBIOS; IPX; DECNET; SNA; X.25; Bisync; Async; Frame Relay SONET.

### **Standards**

XML; HTML 5; CSS 3; SOAP; WSDL; 802.11b; UML; GSM; TDMA; CDMA; OSI; TCP/IP; UDP/IP; X.25; X.400; X.435; X.500; ANSI X.12; TDCC; WINS; CUSDEC; TDC311; EDIFACT.

# **Security Clearance**

**Top Secret** 

## **PROFESSIONAL HISTORY**

## **Chapeau Agricultural Society (Contract)**

2012 (4 months)

### Web Developer/Designer

Developed and implemented the Chapeau Agricultural Society web site. A Wordpress based implementation; the CAS site involved a very specific look and feel as well as a need to ensure the customer could maintain the site after implementation. Requirements were elicited and documented during customer meetings and prototypes developed and presented for approval. After a model was selected the site was developed utilizing WordPress, Using the HTML5 and CSS3 Web Standards. Training documentation was also developed and training given in maintaining the site.

### **xwave Corporation.**, St. John's, Newfoundland and Labrador; Ottawa, Ontario

2004 - 2010

### Company Security Officer

As ACSO Mr. Wilkins ensured that the organization complied with the Public Works and Government Services Canada (PWGSC) Industrial Security Program (ISP), the Controlled Goods Directorate (CGD) and by the International Traffic in Arms Regulations (ITAR) regulations, in particular 22 C.F.R. Chapter I, Subchapter M, parts 120-130. On the acquisition of the xwave organization by CAE, Mr. Wilkins took the lead role in harmonizing the separate organization's policies and procedures into new unified documents and led the training effort to disseminate the new policies.

### Senior Systems Engineer / Technical Architect

Mr Wilkins created and delivered solutions meeting clients' needs utilizing INCOSE system engineering standards (SIMILAR) and the Rational Unified Process for clients as diverse as DND through civilian aviation companies to

distilleries. In all cases he has standardized processes to develop business models; elicit and analyse requirements; design, test, implement and deploy solutions for his clients. Mr. Wilkins lead teams of highly skilled developers and technical resources while managing such diverse projects as developing an office and manufacturing control and inventory system for a leading American distillery, to re-developing a safety management system for a global Air Services organization.

During this time, Mr. Wilkins also mentored other employees in the organization in the Rational Unified Process and how it could be implemented in their project work; and regularly contributed to Request for Proposal responses.

# Innovapost Corporation., Ottawa, Ontario

2001 - 2004

### Senior Consultant - Technology Architect / Business Analyst

Mr Wilkins participated in over 16 projects during this time as well as providing counselling and mentoring to other members of the Technology Architecture team. He worked with clients to develop the business and functional requirements, leveraged existing, or engineered new solutions designed to extend Canada Post's relationships with its business partners and employees in directions that will place it in the forefront of postal organizations worldwide.

During this period Mr. Wilkins worked on projects ranging from a leading edge SAP implementation of Event Manager; through a web based solution providing an interactive SAP HR site to 65,000 employees; through a web services solution for manifest submission by large volume mailers; through utilizing middleware solutions for data transformation and message queuing; to implementing WIFI solutions for mail sorting plants.

### **Ericsson Communications Canada, Ottawa, Ontario**

1998 - 2001

Senior Consultant / Solutions Architect

### Rogers AT&T Wireless Portal, Toronto, Ontario

Developed a solution to provide data services to Roger's new subscribers resulting in a state of the art Portal capable of being expanded to support over 2 million users utilizing both wire-line and wireless technologies. A J2EE solution, based on rendering XML, the portal offers true device independence.

### Ericsson Canada Employee Personal Portal Project, Ottawa, Ontario

Led the pre-study of the project which required the evaluation of all Ericsson wireless products in terms of business needs, and a business case justification of those selected for implementation. It required investigation and recommendation of a middleware implementation to integrate multiple backend systems such as Peoplesoft, SAP and internal financial and delivery systems. Architectural designs and standards were utilized to provide a clear and concise summary of the findings.

### Ericsson E-Business Initiative, Stockholm Sweden & Dallas Texas USA

Over a two-year span, Mr. Wilkins developed the architecture for a platform to support Ericsson's web based business model for the 21st Century. Working on-site in Stockholm and Dallas Mr. Wilkins guided a team of ten full time and six part time e-Business architects, spread between two major business and IT hubs. He defined and directed the implementation of the robust Enterprise level tools and processes required for Ericsson to securely share its business critical applications with its business partners. Ericsson's estimated cost savings of moving to a web based business environment amount to several billion SEK annually.

#### Dealt with issues such as:

- Network design of a three-hub solution including proxies, caching, DNS, routing, layered security, firewalls, extreme switches and system management.
- Development of an XML based API layer in IBM's WebSphere J2EE environment for integration of system services and backend heritage systems for pricing, order management, configuration etc. utilizing Java Beans, Enterprise Java Beans and middleware based transformation and transaction processing.
- A single sign on security architecture utilizing rules and roles, LDAP services and multilevel metadata constructs in web content.
- Evaluation and selection of a content management system based on editorial control and workflow with integration to existing content stores.

• Over all, identification and development of the business model, the functional, non-functional, operational, network and security architectures as well as capacity design and Service Level Agreements with existing Ericsson business units and service areas.

### iSTAR Internet Inc., Ottawa, Ontario

1996-1998 (18 Months)

### Product Development Architect

Leveraged Project Management skills to architect, implement and run the production level iCOMMERCE initiative, a secure, UNIX based electronic transaction manager to support electronic commerce over the Internet. Responsibilities included platform design, including integration of multiple individual products into a cohesive whole; acquisition of hardware and software; physical and logical security; coordination of sub-contractors and participating banks; management of the installation and support personnel; customer and channel training and support. Also provided technical support for iCOMMERCE networking and security, and provided pre-sales support for the marketing and sales departments in the area of Electronic Commerce.

# National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, NASA,

1996 (4 months)

Project Manager

Working on-site in Washington D.C. Mr. Wilkins developed the project plan to upgrade the satellite control network for NOAA to a state of the art multi-protocol routed Wide Area Network. He was also called upon to chair the status meetings for NOAA management, negotiate work commitments with various production and support groups, provide detailed implementation scripts and project plans, coordinate the activities and deliverables of all sub-contractors and negotiate the financial and contractual requirements of equipment acquisition.

### OTHER PREVIOUS EXPERIENCE

Details can be provided as required.

Botano cari do providos do requiros.

Information Systems Management, Ottawa, Ontario

morniacion systems management, setawa, site

Revenue Canada, Ottawa, Ontario

Petro-Canada, Calgary, Alberta

Industry Canada, Ottawa, Ontario

Business Process Analyst / Project Manager

Senior Network Consultant

Network Architect / Consultant/ Project Leader

Manager / Network Planner

### **EDUCATION/TRAINING:**

Algonquin College, Ottawa Ontario, Graduate Certificate in Interactive Multimedia	2012
University of Carleton, Ottawa Ontario; Faculty of Arts	1990
University of Calgary, Calgary, Alberta; Computer Science	1980-1983
University of Alberta, Edmonton Alberta; Faculty of Arts (BA Degree)	1975
University of Alberta, Edmonton Alberta; Faculty of Engineering	1973

### **Additional Training:**

Formal Training in the Rational Unified Process.

Formal training in PROPS, PMI and Kepner Tregoe Project Management Methodologies.

A variety of industry specific cellular courses, including WAP gateways and wireless applications.

Multiple electronic commerce products (ie InterWorld, Open Market and Ariba).

Various industry training including Voice, (telephony), Cisco routers, Network Switches, Oracle and SQL database, programming languages, etc.

A wide variety of Managerial training.